this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software
[Music]
hello this is Adam Gordon bell for
software engineering radio today I'm
speaking with Stephen Wolfram Stephen is
scientist creator of Wolfram language
Mathematica also Wolfram Alpha and the
CEO of Wolfram research Stephen welcome
to software engineering radio thank you
so you have this new book adventures of
a computational explorer but I thought
it might be fun to start talking about
Mathematica and some of the programming
language work you've done and maybe
we'll get to some of the interesting
book stuff towards the latter part sure
sure the book is kind of my strange
adventures that come from taking the
computational paradigm seriously so to
speak I want to start maybe with some
basics
what is Mathematica what is Wolfram
language like where did they come from
what's the goal where did they come from
when I was a kid I was interested in
physics and discovered that you could
learn a lot of stuff about something
like physics just by reading books now
with the internet but back then it was
just books and really wanted to do
physics research and really didn't like
doing the kind of mechanical
mathematical calculations that you
needed to do for physics research so I
kind of very early on got this idea this
was back in the Oh probably 1973 or
something got this when I was like 13
years old so so I'm old now
and the you know kind of got this idea
that this was something that was boring
a mechanical for humans surely one could
just automate it and get computers to do
it so that got me kind of on the path of
how can I oughta mate things like
mathematical computation and make them
be doable by computer and my first
language which is called SMP symbolic
manipulation program sort of one of its
important features was that it was
dealing with everything symbolically so
you know an X you can just say type in X
and it comes back as X it's perfectly
happy to just deal with X as a symbolic
he doesn't say oh no error just needs to
have a value and so on and in SNP I kind
of know I would say I I tried out some
fairly radical ideas about thinking
about programs as being primarily
transformations on symbolic expressions
that sort of everything like when you
evaluate a function what are you doing
you're really transforming f of X to
whatever the value of the function is
and thinking about that as transforming
a symbolic expression from the input to
the output so to speak um that was the
primary operation of the language so
that sounds a lot like like Lisp I guess
to me a little bit I mean except that
one of the things that so so certainly
Lisp I would say that that in the early
days Lisp an APL my two kind of most you
know languages that were kind of most
relevant sort of design you know
inspirations along with C I guess I mean
C SMP was kind of I I started using C as
the implementation language for SMP back
in 1979 before C was really so much of a
thing and the person who persuaded me to
do that was a student who was sort of
working with me at the time named Rob
Pike who went a lotta build them go and
was has always been a minimalist and at
that time was like C is the language of
the future there's a little micro
footnote to history for you but the
difference is that in code of the
symbolic languages I deal with it you
kind of take seriously the fact that you
can just have symbolic stuff lying
around and that there is an automatic
infinite evaluation that occurs whenever
it can
it's a little different from kind of the
way one thinks about evaluation and
something like Lisp Oh what does that
mean like I I don't follow what does it
mean for a valuation to be infinite
we're by the way still at the very early
stages of the story here so there's
there's much more to say so I mean what
it means is if you have defined a series
of transformation rules that define you
know ones used to doing this with
functions ones less used to doing it
with variables but those really aren't
any different in open language and in
the kind of symbolic framework that we
have but
basically the the idea is that one if
you give some input then what will
happen is transformation rules will
occur to the until you reach a fixed
point basically and that's the results
of your computation so you know whenever
you type in if you go ask Siri some
question that goes to off alpha you know
the natural language will be turned into
Wolfram language symbolic language and
then what will happen sort of under the
hood at some low level is there'll be a
whole giant series of transformation
rules applied and in the end there will
be some fixed point reached and that's
the result and then you know it will say
back to you whatever it says the answer
is so to speak I mean that's a that's
the very low-level version of of what's
happening now you know the user
experience I have to say I I don't think
I've talked about infinite evaluation in
in decades because it seems natural to
people and so nobody ever says oh that's
but since you brought up Lisp I remember
when when SMP and Len later mathematical
movement language were we young people
would sometimes say it's impossible it
can't work you can't build a system that
has infinite evaluation and and they're
thinking about things like if you type x
equals x plus 1 what does it do oh I see
I see now yeah and it turns out well you
know it runs into some limit and turns
out nobody cares it turns out it's what
one of the features of language design
it's kind of interesting to me is always
these things where so you know one of my
mehta claims about language design the
only language design in which nothing
weird could ever happen is a language
which does absolutely nothing and so the
question is the places where weird
things happen are they things that
people actually run into in practice or
not and turns out that I can say after I
don't know 40 years or something that
that's one where it turns out nobody
cares it turns out people don't run into
it in writing real programs and even
though from a theoretical point of view
the something where you could say oh my
gosh there's this corner you could run
into it it would be terrible
type thing and it's undefined what
happens that's not sort of the important
thing in practice but this is really a
footnote to a footnote about some the
relationship to Lisp and it's evaluation
strategy as I said it's probably one of
the least important features of kind of
the whole tower of stuff that that I've
tried to build well so I was just asking
you because like as a software engineer
you know I try to like look at languages
and figure out you know what family it
fits in like where that helps me find
have a context for you know how you
solve problems and in this world yeah I
think in the if we were talking about it
well from language as a like human
languages it would be an isolate well
you know I would say it it has ideas
from many languages and many languages
now have taken ideas from it actually
but its goals are very different from
the traditional programming languages
when you can use it as a quotes
programming language but that is kind of
to get only a small part of the value
that it has to offer so to speak and I
think you know the big story has to do
with being able to express all sorts of
things computationally and for
Mathematica I kind of cleaned up and
extended my kind of ideas about
computational languages and in the end
we kind of have rebranded the language
and the stuff that Mathematica does as
Wolfram language because I got so fed up
with people just saying I don't do math
I don't need to use your stuff I think
that helps me understand you created
this to help with math but it became a
much wider thing and so you've rebranded
it from Mathematica
it's a Wolfram language so who's the
primary user of it now is it still
within the science math domain or well I
mean it's it's been around so since it's
been around for 31 years it's got lots
of people who have used it for a long
long time so like you know there are
site licenses for our technology at
basically all the major universities in
the US and many outside the US as well
it gets used by you know R&D folk it's
always really neat to me that kind of
the world's highest end the R&D folk
turn out unbeknownst to me when I run
into them
like oh yeah I've used your products for
20 years type thing which is really neat
I would say that it's it's widely used
in the R&D sphere particularly kind of
the high-end of R&D widely used in
higher education as we move forward it
gets progressively used in sort of more
general production and enterprise
settings and that's been kind of the
story of the last few years is setting
up Wolfram language so that it is really
deployable in the cloud and embedded
settings as some in different kinds of
containerized mechanisms and so on so
that it can really be integrated into
sort of large-scale production systems
and it is integrated now into a whole
bunch of large-scale production systems
in sort of the the fortune 50 companies
and elsewhere so the the typical use of
whorfin language we invented these
things called notebooks that have become
quite popular finally in recent years
but we invented them in exactly the form
basically that they exist today and in
back in 1988 when the first version of
Mathematica came out it's actually one
of the things I really like is that I
can take a mathematical version one
notebook and I can run it you know in in
version 12 of Wolfram language or in the
cloud and it actually works which is
very encouraging to me and important to
me because actually I'm for example just
working on a big basic science project
right now where I did a little bit on it
in the mid-1990s a little bit on it and
around 2004 and now I'm sort of
restarting this and by golly the
notebooks that I created at those times
still run well then so I mean Wolfram
language has been very consistent it's
one of the very few examples of a
language where code that people wrote in
version 1 back in 1988 still runs today
and it's a heavy burden as a language
designer because it's like you don't get
to make too many mistakes if you want
that to happen and far into the future
so to speak I'd like to talk at some
point about about the language design
aspects of it but I don't want to skip
over notebooks because super interesting
area that you were obviously a pioneer
in so could you describe what this
notebook approach to computing is maybe
explain it to people who aren't familiar
yeah yeah it's it's it's very simple
it's
kind of how you interact with the
computation so the the basic thing
you're doing is you're saying to the
when you're computing you're basically
saying there's input there's output you
say what's 2+2 you press shift enter
comes back as 4 but that's part of a
document and the notebook document can
have text and section headings and you
know we made it have you know
hierarchical structure back from the
very beginning and it's it's organized
in this collection of cells and so each
piece of like input and output is a cell
each and then there could be like
section heading cells and those will
automatically group things underneath
them so you like double-click the
section heading cell and it will close
itself up in an outline so what you're
describing
it's like Wolfram language is not a text
files that get run by an interpreter
Wolfram languages is like oh you know
something like an interactive word doc
or Excel document where you can execute
code in it and have visual elements is
that sure but yes the the I mean for
example when I use Wolfram language I
mean like this morning I was writing a
bunch of code and you know it's in
notebooks in fact the particular some of
the particular notebooks I was writing
will get ingested into our function
repository so that when people use them
they will just be define they'll just be
functions that they defined that they'll
just use those functions and they could
always go look at the source notebook if
they wanted to but as far as they're
concerned it doesn't really make any
difference that that code was written in
a notebook as opposed to written in a
text file and I'm sure a lot of people
listening were thinking of Jupiter
notebooks and is that inspired by your
work well calling to Fernando Perez he
says he took Mathematica notebooks and
made a version of them for Python yeah I
think they're they don't have a lot of
the features that our notebooks have but
yes they came from from our stuffing in
great detail actually I mean even the
detail prompts are the same and so on
but I'm not I'm not an expert on them
because I I don't use them although you
can call or from language from from
inside Jupiter these days you can call
our Wolfram engine system that way if
you want to fact you can even call a
free wolf management
helped us from inside Jupiter oh very
cool so it's it's very interesting this
approach to computing what like what
advantages is this notebook format give
you when you're when you're coding well
I mean sort of everything happens
instantly I mean I've got you know I
press shift enter and then I run the
code and it's right there and I've got
my sort of test examples right there so
to speak and I mean the other thing that
is a huge advantage in Wolfram language
which is probably not so obvious unless
you've experienced it is that in a
symbolic language every piece of code
runs on its own everything stands on its
own so you can always take any piece of
code out of any other piece of code and
it is runnable separately you don't need
to build a harness for it it is just a
runnable executable thing I mean that's
a I would say what tends to happen is
that people write sort of small-scale
algorithmic things directly in notebooks
by the time one's working on large-scale
multi-user sort of source controlled
software projects people tend to go to
using some IDE you know we have one
couple from workbench that's based on
Eclipse but they're a bunch of other IDs
that work with orphan language and
people will then you know by the time
it's huge blobs of code it tends to be
using more traditional IDE type
technology but the thing that for you
know for doing exploratory work
notebooks are the best I mean that's
what you know for doing data science for
doing R&D I mean for data science the
key thing is that what you use to
develop things is what you use to
deliver your final report so I'm very
big on this idea of computational essays
which are kind of ways to it's sort of a
new form of explaining things but you
have a little piece of code a little
piece of text and then you'll have a
piece of computational language and its
output and the idea is that when you're
explaining what's going on you're mixing
kind of the explanation with natural
language with human language and the
explanation from computational language
now again that sort of depends a little
bit
on our technology stack but the end
result I mean that's you know it's kind
of what I've been doing for oh I don't
know 30-something years including I've
done quite a lot of basic science over
that period of time and that's kind of
how I've done that is everything is kind
of set up in in notebooks and in these
computational essays where I'm kind of
explaining what's happening to myself or
to other people but the you know the
full code is there and everything is
runnable and actually something that we
now have available is notebook
publishing so you can take come take one
of these notebooks that you created
either on the desktop or in the cloud
and you can publish it and we just
provide a server that allows you to to
freely publish notebooks so that people
can then anybody in the world can go to
a published notebook it's just a way it
just comes up as a web page and can
interact with it so they can you know
resize the graphics they can rotate the
3d images they can move the sliders and
them in the manipulates and so on and
they can sort of open and close cell
groups and things like that and then
there's a button that says make your own
copy and if you make your own copy then
you get an editable version of the
notebook that you can then go and and
start modifying the code modifying
whatever you want to modify and redo the
computations so I think this is a it's a
really really powerful way of sort of
integrating both the doing of things
like data science and the deployment and
the kind of presenting of results from
things like data science I was looking
at some examples of these computational
essays to try to wrap my head around is
it's a pretty interesting thing so it
strikes me as it's something like like a
way to do scientific papers but even
maybe more casually so I found one that
was like talking about the civil war or
something and and it had like paragraphs
talking about where the various battles
are and then it had some Wolfram code
that was like it basically like pulled
out the locations of the battles and
like threw them on a map so it was kind
of an interactive essay kind of
explaining it but what are some other
interesting examples of kind of
combining you know prose and encode oh
gosh I mean there are tons of them
there's a there's a whole
Notebook archive that were in the
process of getting up that Chum has well
has examples you know the really weird
thing about it is it has examples that
were written in like 1990 and so on and
that's still run and although some of
the the styling of the text looks pretty
ugly and we're trying to we're grappling
with that right now but but that's
that's a minor issue so to speak but you
know it could be about anything I mean
the thing you just mentioned of course
the fact that that works depends on the
fact that in Wolfram language we have a
knowledge base which knows about the
battles in the Civil War for example so
you're not going out and saying oh let
me go find some data and clean it up and
all that kind of thing so another
important thing about Wolfram language
is the language is this precise symbolic
language but one way of inputting pieces
of the language is using natural
language so you know in a notebook you
type control equals and then you might
type battles in the Civil War
and then as soon as you hit enter it
will turn into the entity American Civil
War and then of the property battles and
so American Civil War is underneath its
entity quotes military conflict comma
quotes American Civil War and then
battles underneath is the entity
property military conflict battles and
if I evaluate that press shift enter I
will get a big long list of entities
like you know the Battle of Westport the
Battle of Fort Stevens and so on each of
these is an entity of a military
conflict entity and each of these is
like a symbolic expression and each of
those symbolic expressions I can do
computations with like for example I can
find out the geo position of it or
something like this and the the but the
whole point in it in a computational
essay is that you're kind of sharing the
load of creating the content because you
know you're writing the English text or
the natural language text you're writing
the computational language input but
then the the computer is automatically
generating the output so you know it's
it's sort of it might be a little bit
more effort to get the computational
language correct you don't get to kind
of
just smoosh the words around like you
would in natural language you actually
have to say something that's kind of
precisely what you mean so to speak but
the good news is that then the computer
kind of generates the output so you
might have a very tiny piece of Wolfram
language code like this one that said
American Civil War battles and then you
get this big long list of battles out
and then I could say gee Oh Lisp lot of
that and I would get a well but you
might think of a geo plot of where all
those battles are so it's kind of the
idea and it's sort of as a programming
language thing it's quite interesting
this interplay between natural language
and the programming language what we
found is that for things like specifying
an entity or something it's really
really useful to have natural language
you don't want to have a manual a piece
of documentation that lists all the
military conflicts in history and says
what they're canonical names are you
just want to type you know Civil War and
let's see if I do that here I think it
will default let's see what it does so
it says the United States Civil War but
then it has a little dot dot dot here
which says alternate interpretations so
it says assuming the United States Civil
War use English Civil War instead so you
can click that to change the
interpretation of that input or you can
also um okay there apparently some other
things a board game a book other other
kinds of things that have are called the
Civil War I want to back up because I
think that you don't realize how
different this is from how most
programming languages work perhaps so
you're saying that oh I I do that's why
I don't call it a programming language
okay okay then so I want to I kind of
want to nail down this data think I
think it's interesting so I'm sitting I
have a Wolfram lang prompt like it's
like a and a repple and I can you know
type programs and ifs and and such but
also I have just like data there sure so
I can do like jupiter-mass or I can do
Civil War or I was playing around with
this actually so there's like food in
there like lemon tart lemon tart
calories like what what where does this
data live why is it in the language
well it's in the language because the
language the purpose of the language is
to express sort of everything in the
world computationally so this data is is
the knowledge base that we built over
the last thirty years or so you know we
have been steadily accumulating curating
making computable data about all sorts
of kinds of things so you'll find a
couple hundred thousand foods foods are
very complicated they have a very
complicated ontology and you know lots
of properties of mote well different
foods have different numbers of
properties because people haven't
necessarily measured the you know the
this content of that but this most will
have you know I don't know twenty or
thirty standard kinds of nutritional
pieces of data about them but so yes we
have or all the things that you know all
sorts of data made computable which is a
very it's a high bar to make data
computable it's not good enough to just
say you know if you're dealing with I
don't know let's say you want to know
about asteroids or something and you
want to compute you know the the largest
ten asteroids or something it's not good
enough to just say well we've got some
asteroids you've got to have sort of all
the asteroids so that you can actually
correctly compute the largest ten
asteroids and this is it takes well
taken a lot of effort to kind of
accumulate all of this data about lots
of kinds of things and then there's lots
of real-time data like all the real-time
weather data or earthquake data or
flight tracking data or whatever else so
how does it work if you have real-time
data like if I do like weather dot now
will it tell me what it's like you know
this dot business is not really the
right thing if you if you say oh say air
temperature data for example that with
the function is for example air
temperature data of and then pick a city
where at where are you
Peterborough Ontario Canada okay let's
try Peterborough let's see what it does
with Peterborough is it Oh
Oh ro ugh oh that's right
um okay Peterborough City okay so it
picked the one in Canada by default for
me so that's an entity so it so for what
it's worth the Peterborough the entity
if I say what is that what is the input
form what what I see on the screen is a
is a yellow background box that has the
word Peterborough and then the word City
after it but if I say what's the input
form of that at
say entities city Peterborough Ontario
Canada okay
hmm so then I can say oh let's say I say
air temperature data that's a function
of Peterborough then I will get Open
bracket where I say a temperature table
to open back at Peterborough I will get
hopefully some result oh it's loading in
some some okay
34 degrees Fahrenheit it says so it's
giving it an Fahrenheit because it knows
I'm in the US if I were to tell it um I
I could just say unit convert that to
centigrade if I wanted to or I could go
ahead and say say air temperature data
of Peterborough comma and then I could
say like now - three weeks when okay so
you have this entity Peterborough and
you get the weather like that's making
some sort of web service call somewhere
that I don't know but like where does
this all live okay so it so it's going
yes it is going to our cloud so whether
data is streaming in from the sources we
use for weather data we're storing all
that stuff and then this behind the
scenes the language is going out to our
cloud to retrieve that data okay and
what if I put in like mass of Stephen
Wolfram like I don't know let's see what
happens that's see them I don't know
whether that Oh Stephen Wolfram wait
let's see missing not available sorry
well at least we understand what the
question means there I I could I could
hook that up actually I because I we
have a we have this notion of data bins
which are again sort of symbolic objects
that live in the cloud and you know I
have a data bin that a bunch of my
personal analytics data is streaming
into and so for example if I went to
that data bin I could actually find out
you know how much I weighed this morning
so to speak but that's not part of the
public database I'm not I'm not doing an
Oprah like that um yeah um maybe that's
too long lost in history that reference
I don't know she was famous for having
talked a lot about her weight on her
television show you talked about Siri
using Wolfram Alpha and you have this
knowledge base like why not pure natural
language you mean forever thing
well okay so so that's a good question
and here's the story if you've got a
sort of simple one-line question you
know how much does Oprah weigh right
something like learnt we can do very
high quality natural language
understanding on that and we can sort of
turn that into some symbolic form we can
compute the answer we can give you the
back the results okay but let's say
you're trying to describe some more
complicated thing let's say you're
trying to define some algorithm and have
it operate on images and do this and
that and the other
very quickly natural language just
completely falls apart and fragments of
it like you say I don't know let's say
you want the depth distribution of the
Pacific Ocean and you want that you know
only pieces that are this far away from
Australia and then you want to know you
want the pieces that are within a
certain distance of volcanoes blah blah
blah saying all of that in natural
language is is hard saying it in
computational language once you know the
computational language is very nice very
easy and when you write it down in
computational language it's easy for
other people to understand it as well
and you know I found this really good
sort of case of this I wrote a book
called elementary introduction to the
Wolfram language which actually was sort
of primarily aimed at kids but has ended
up being widely used by people other
than kids and as well as kids but I
decided to put exercises in this book
and the exercise is basically have the
form of write a piece of Wolfram
language code that does X and at the
beginning of the book was really easy to
do that to write those exercises but by
the end of the book it was super
frustrating because you know I
immediately knew the code I want you
know here's how to express what I'm
talking about and Wolfram language in
computational language but you know to
be able to write that in English was
actually pretty tough would you say that
your goals are that it is like a
communication tool or is is the goal to
be able to communicate to
futures are to be able to communicate to
each other using computers both both yes
I mean you know in in the case of look
15 million lines of code inside wolf
alpha is you know that's not intended to
be read by a human yeah um but the
things that you write in computational
essays absolutely those are intended to
be read by by humans but also executed
by machine
so it's it's a language that you know
scales very nicely from very small to
very large and you know the small pieces
the sort of human sized pieces are
absolutely great ways of communicating I
would say that one of the things that I
consider important about the language
we've built is that it is a language for
thinking about things computationally in
mmm so what does that mean you know when
I try and imagine how to specify
something I can immediately know oh that
you know fold pair list is likely to be
the functional programming construct
that I want to use and I can know that
you know I obviously use this language a
long time um that that is a way of
organizing my thoughts about what I'm
trying to do if I didn't have that kind
of primitive
I wouldn't organize my thoughts that way
I mean I see this all the time because I
see it particularly as we develop the
language and as we finally condense a
bunch of ideas into some new primitive
in the language I suddenly realize oh
all these things that I was thinking
about in this kind of mushy way before I
can think about all of those kinds of
things just using this that's a
particular functional programming
primitive it's a thinking tool you're
you're building some sort of Augmented
ability by using a computer to be able
to reason about the world yes I see our
computational language is something that
helps organize human thoughts as well as
defining to machines what we want them
to do I mean in other words you know if
you look at sort of the the arc of
history on these kinds of things a good
analogy is mathematical notation so back
400 years ago or something when people
were
talking about math they didn't have a
notation they didn't have plus signs and
equal signs and so on they they just
used words mm-hmm
and it was kind of clunky and then
people started inventing mathematical
notation and what happened fairly soon
thereafter was algebra got invented and
then after that calculus and so on and
basically the sort of mathematically
based sciences were made possible by the
invention of this kind of notation that
allowed people to organize their
mathematical thoughts and communicate
them and in a sense what what what we're
trying to do what I'm trying to do with
Wolfen language is to provide a kind of
notation for computational thinking and
you know I think it's it's doing a good
job at starting to enable a lot of these
kind of computational X fields just as
kind of mathematical notation eventually
enabled the kind of mathematical X
fields I think the the big difference
between our computational language and
mathematical language mathematical
notation is with math notation you're
still stuck with a poor human having to
interpret the things the great thing
about computational language is once you
write it down you know then a machine AI
whatever you want to call it computer
can take it away and do things with it
and that's that's really powerful and I
think that the you know the way I see it
this is a it's a form of communication
the exploratory aspects are really where
you're the most unique it strikes me
like I don't know of another
computational SI tool
have you tried you know like bringing
this to to youth or people who aren't
familiar with computer programming
because I because I talked about feeding
this to kids I actually feel like I have
to do some field work so I actually
spend a couple of hours doing that with
actual middle school kids and so on it's
actually it's a it's a lovely contrast
from what I normally do for a living of
CEO in a technology company but yes
absolutely it's a I mean it's something
where you know you can get to do
computational X you can get to really do
sort of original non-trivial
computational things about the world
about topics you care about and you
don't have to learn her right for loops
and so on I mean it's kind of kind of
shocking in the little book that I wrote
about about Wolfram language it has a
know 50 chapters or something and I
think assigning values to variables
doesn't show up until chapter 38 and I
don't think loops I I don't believe
loops ever show up I mean they obviously
show up implicitly it's some you know
there's the function table shows up very
very early and map shows up pretty early
but but I don't think no I'm pretty sure
do does not occur in the book and it's
sort of interesting that I've explained
what we call function functions which
are basically lambdas long before I had
to explain assigning values to variables
and so on but so the main point is with
often language one gets to actually sort
of do things computationally without
sort of going through learning kind of
the low-level computer science the
traditional low level programming
language computer science stuff you know
I would say that in in terms of of kids
we do we've been doing for quite a few
years a a high school summer camp hmm
and it's always fun to go look on the
web you'll see the projects that the
kids have done at the summer camp and
they're quite impressive usually I'm I
don't know he can go um pull it up and I
can I can see what some of those were
from last year so I pulled one up
earlier I think I think it was from this
thing but the one I found was it was
this essay I guess but there was
building a piano and then at the end
there was a little piano on the screen
that you could like click on the notes
and play it yeah that's I would say that
was that's fun but that's in the sense
one of the more traditional kinds of
from you know you could imagine doing
that in a bunch of other program okay I
pulled up the ones for this year so the
first one was analyzing global global
emoji use and I guess this was looking
at Twitter and pulling out emoji and
making a plot on a map of which
countries have happy and sad emoji the
second one seemed to read tracking
algorithm for squash okay so that I
remember that one actually that one was
a I didn't think that one was going to
work but
it worked worked rather well it was
taking video images and finding the
trajectories of squash balls and video
images oh wow
looked like um another one here
automatic evaluation of relationships
between characters and plays so I
suspect that was a combination of
natural language processing I see on the
screen here a nice community graph plots
these are high school kids these are
high school kids yeah this this sounds
like something that I wouldn't be able
to do well but that's the point that's
that's the cool thing it is a remarkable
thing that what gets taught in you know
kind of I don't know when you when you
get taught about computation in and you
think well I'm getting taught computer
science I'm learning how to do for loops
and so on but that's not really what's
involved in doing sort of computational
thinking for a real purpose I mean I
think that um you know I'm sure in one
of these I don't know like the the
example here of okay evaluating
relationships between characters in
plays I'm sure what actually came up
there I can click on it find out what
was what was what happened there but I'm
sure what actually came up was all sorts
of things about how do you find given
the text of a play how do you actually
pick out you know what were the you know
what was the description of you know
this is a character how do you find the
boundaries of the scenes and so on and
each one of these things there's
probably some idea that you can have oh
well if there's a you know paragraph
break between this and this that
probably represents that okay so the
trick is you know can you easily go from
that idea to an actual piece of
computational language code that
implements it and the whole point is to
have primitives that a high enough level
that the things you think in terms of
are the primitives that are provided in
the language you're not having to think
how do I break down that thought into
you know sort of linked lists and array
references and listen that and the other
you're rather thinking oh I want to
break up the text into sentences okay
there's a there's a function called text
sentences that does that etc and and you
know in terms of language design the big
sort of challenge I suppose is you know
there are now six
thousand built-in functions in Wolfram
language and kind of my big job over the
last three decades has been sort of
keeping the design of these things
coherent and consistent so that you know
once you know about how things work with
text or something you are immediately
helped in in understanding how things
gonna work with images of graphs or
whatever else and I think one of the one
of the processes actually it's been kind
of fun so you know I've been doing a
language design and design reviews for
four decades now in the last year and a
half I've started doing something kind
of fun with these which is you know
pretty much every day I'll be doing some
design reviews for working out various
kinds of language design and I started
about a year and a half ago
live-streaming a bunch of these things
and so now there's I think I just did my
300th episode of live streamed design
reviews yeah this is this is kind of
wild so I I watch one of these so you
you are just on Twitch just like meeting
with people and and trying to like like
live coding like you've been doing a
little bit here and playing around with
the language and making decisions what
is the live element add to it you know I
wasn't sure I thought what we're doing
is kind of interesting it might be fun
for people why not put it out there and
see what happens it turns out we've
started to get lots of sophisticated
users of our products and experts and
all kinds of things who you know login
and they make real suggestions and
they're pretty useful and that's a you
know it's a pretty nice dynamic and
they'll send all code fragments and so
on and you know send references to
papers to look at and things like that
that's you know that's one unexpected
feature another thing is actually the
archives of these things are pretty
useful for us internally um I think
they're also useful for people who are
using our language and want to learn how
to do design of things in our language
so for example we recently started this
thing we call our function repository
and it's a question of you know that
function repository is supposed to
follow our design principles
well if you
to understand the thought processes that
go into our design principles then these
live streams are a good sort of source
of that of understanding that I think um
you know it's also it kind of is you
know when people say I want to come work
at your company what's it like okay you
can you know this there's whatever it is
six hundred hours of live stream these
things you can you can find out what
it's like you like it you don't like it
you know whatever we've done a few live
streams with some outside experts and
were probably doing more of those that's
kind of an interesting dynamic you know
we have plenty of in-house experts on
plenty of things but sometimes we're
trying to learn about stuff that that we
don't have a lot of internal expertise
about but I think um yeah it's I mean
the the main dynamic about design
reviews is more sort of the underlying
process which is you know it's all about
sort of drilling down what is language
design really about it's really about
sort of imagining all the different
kinds of programs all the different
kinds of things people might want to
represent in one's language and trying
to kind of drill things down to some
essential features that allow one to
sort of define the right primitives from
which all that stuff will be built up
and in a sense for me you know I've
worked on a bunch of different kinds of
things in my life in science and
technology and so on but for me I think
language design is the most pure kind of
pure focused intellectual activity that
I know because it's really it's all
about what is the essence of what's
going on in something and how do you
represent that and it's you know it's
often hard work if you get it right
you know honestly people don't even
notice it's the it's the little places
that are braids because you got it wrong
that the people will notice and say oh
you know it doesn't seem to work quite
right type thing if you get it right
it's just like oh of course that's how
it works
and people sort of don't really notice
the language design if the language
design is good
they only notice and pleasantly by the
fact that they can be very productive in
what they're doing and it's pretty neat
actually watching people I don't know
particularly the younger crowd who seem
to be often very very fast
at writing things in movement language
we actually have a live coding
competition that we do at our annual
technology conference in a few other
places we just did one of those and I
was some I didn't compete in it I
decided I shouldn't do that because I
think I wouldn't win and one of my kids
actually is also I think has to be
disqualified because he's too quick at
writing or from language code but but I
think it is quite impressive and
interesting to see how quickly quite
non-trivial kinds of computational
things can be done by people who know
the language well that's very satisfying
to a language designer so for example
one could even imagine you know if the
language is well designed then the
typical thing you want to write will be
a nice extinct piece of code and if
there's this weird you know blob off the
end of the code that's probably a bug
yeah that makes sense but there's
there's varying use cases I guess like
I'm thinking of ok Jupiter should that
be Jupiter the god or shouldn't be
Jupiter the planet or right well so so
let's see what happens if we type that
in so if I say control equals Jupiter
okay so it defaults the planet it has
little dot dot dot here it says assuming
Jupiter is a planet use as a
mythological figure or a given name or
referring to a fictional character
instead so at the stage of input if you
give natural language input at the stage
of input it will do that disambiguation
once you've pressed there's a check
check mark next to the the little yellow
box here once you press that check mark
you will then get an a definite so let's
say I pick mythological figure instead
okay the way it works since it's called
the ambiguity function as part of the
these things for interpreters which are
part of the language which are the way
that Tim sort of that's the symbolic
representation of the process of
interpretation but in the case it's it's
always working the same way of if you're
using natural language and and there's
you know like for example in the stuff I
was doing on my physics project I
suspect I was writing Wolfram language
code for hours without touching anything
in natural language the
no reason to because it's some cuz it's
precise or yeah it's because because I'm
thinking about it in Wolfram language
basically and I'm not trying to relate
it to things that I best better can
express a natural language now now maybe
if I was sort of a if I never used the
language before there might be things
that I would like to type in a natural
language because I that way I can just
use natural language and not not have to
go you know and maybe it saves me from
from trying to understand the
computational language myself at first
but I think very quickly I mean that you
know kind of the other another sort of
idea of language design is you know
whorfin language is a very big language
it's you know it's something there's no
other you know that no programming
language is this big nothing like this
big I mean it they might have a few tens
of key words you know we have six
thousand in in many cases very
complicated highly sort of functions
with many of them are kind of super
functions that you know like there might
be one called classify well there is one
called classify that just uses machine
learning to classify things so that's a
sort of a big super function so to speak
so there but there are 6,000 of these
things and the question is how can one
deal with something that big and the
answer is by making everything very
consistent so people have to learn only
a small set of principles and then are
kind of often running with sort of low
cognitive load they can kind of deal
with other parts of the system once they
know those principles now it's a huge
amount of work to maintain those
principles and and here's what I
realized you you look at these libraries
I don't know it might be Python
libraries or they might be Java
libraries or whatever else and there'll
be a few really core functions that are
really the things people care about in
those libraries but then there'll be a
lot of stuff that has to support those
things let's say it's a thing where
you're doing some particular operation
on images well there's all kinds of
things in that library for reading in
images and writing out images and
converting formats of images and this
that and the other and what typically
happens is that or maybe you include
some other library that
a bunch of those things and so on you
are you know you've got a lot of work to
do to sort of deal with the
infrastructure of what's going on before
you get to your you know your master
function so to speak you at your top
function and what I realized in the
function repository that we built I I
wasn't sure it was going to happen with
it and it's actually working really
great that people can add just these
single functions that do very powerful
things and they can just add that one
function because all of the support
stuff is already in the language they
don't have to oh say oh how am I going
to represent the image well there is a
you know this is a way to represent
images they don't have to they don't
have to sort of rebuild the
infrastructure every time they want to
get to a piece of functionality so that
makes it possible and it also helps a
lot having a symbolic language where you
can kind of have different kinds of
things that are manipulate in a very
uniform way because everything is a
symbolic expression you know an image is
a symbolic expression a user interfaces
a symbolic expression a cloud object is
a symbolic expression if I ask you about
the language you're like yeah its
batteries included it has everything and
that could be like oh you mean like
image processing and you're like well
image processing but also Oprah Winfrey
yeah right right you know what we've
done for better or worse it's a very
unique thing and I have only you know
this idea of trying to make a really
integrated sort of full scale
computational language it just hasn't
been the ambition or the activity
basically anybody else and I've been you
know it's I'm not sure I would you know
I've since I've spent a large fraction
of my life doing this you know it's I
can say it's been hard work I mean you
have to you have to kind of keep at it
sort of every day for decades to do this
and I think it probably matters that you
know I've personally kept at it and it's
had sort of consistent leadership over a
long period of time I think that you
know it's it's a sort of a strange set
of circumstances that have made that
possible and in a sense
we've you know the thing that we've bit
enough to do is a big thing it strikes
me that like you you have just built
like what you wanted you you've built
this whole company in language around
this idea of building this tool that's
how you want to like think about the
world or the questions you want to ask
of the world that yeah at all right
that's that's true I'm I built something
that I wanted to use and I built
something that for me has proved to be a
a wonderful kind of mechanism for
helping me kind of define my thoughts
about things and you know I'm glad to
see it's useful to other people too I
think that it's it's something where
it's kind of when we when we think about
what's possible with computation and
what's possible with AI and so on
there's this big issue of sort of desert
there's an ocean of possibilities with
computation and actually I happen to
have spent a bunch of time studying sort
of the basic science of that of sort of
what can happen in the computational
universe of all possible programs and so
on and there are lots of really amazing
elaborate things that can happen some of
which the natural world happens to use
much of which the natural world doesn't
use much of which we've never used in
our technology and so on and the
question really is given the sort of
ocean of possibilities that computation
provides you know how do we define which
ones we care about what we actually want
to do and I kind of see computational
language as being the way that we make a
bridge between what is sort of
theoretically possible with computation
and the things that we humans happen to
care about I mean in a sense the things
we happen to care about represent the
sort of slice defined by our
civilizational history relative to what
is conceivable so to speak I mean
there's there's some and in a sense sort
of the language design is is that bridge
between what is computationally
conceivable and what it is and the ways
that we humans like to think about
things and the kinds of things we choose
to think about so to speak that makes
sense
like the temperature
in Peterborough I guess it's somewhat
arbitrary but it's something that is
useful for us as humans because exactly
exactly I mean the very concept of
Peterborough is something that is a
human construct him and we could say the
geolocation on the earth that we could
say you know all kinds of things I mean
the fact that we're choosing that as
opposed to you know the well you know
temperature is a you know we could ask
for something about the dispersion of
the velocities of the gas molecules in
um which wouldn't be whereas the
temperature is you know kind of the
average velocity of the gas molecules we
could ask for something something
different than that and just doesn't
happen to be something we care very much
about the thing that you realize so you
know I've spent a bunch of time sort of
studying the basic science of extremely
simple programs and what they do and
kind of the remarkable thing is that
even programs that you can define in
sort of you know half a line of Wolfram
language code or you can just say you
know you got a row of black and white
cells and based on the color of each
cell and the color of neighboring cells
do this on the next step type thing with
a little table you know just with
programs that simple it's really easy to
find examples where the programs do
really complicated things that one would
never expect from just looking at the
program now some of those programs will
make I don't know nice nested patterns
some of them do things that we can
immediately say oh that'd be useful for
image processing or something but many
of them just do what they do and it's
just like okay that's nice we humans
don't have any particular reason to care
about it I mean sometimes people use
them to make artistic works or something
like this where kind of the the thing
that's important about it from point of
view of us humans is that we find is
aesthetic or something like this but you
know there's this as I say there's this
huge realm of a possible computation out
there and the question is which parts of
it we care about I mean this this you
know I've spent a bunch of time sort of
studying kind of the the total universe
of simple programs in the case of neural
nets and deep learning and so on we're
dealing with more complicated programs
but
and ones were kind of incrementally
exploring by sort of an evolutionary
type technique or a kind of a gradual
adaptation type technique we're kind of
exploring the space of possible programs
and again we ask the question you know
of all the conceivable arrangements of
weights in a neural network or something
which are the ones we care about which
are the ones that do something that is
of relevance to us you know we train an
image identifier we're training it on
things that actually occur in our world
we could as well train an image
identifier on something that is
completely bizarrely you know these
bizarre abstract shapes or patterns or
whatever mm-hmm but you know but then we
don't have a that doesn't connect with
things we care about and for example in
the case of an image identifier we
wouldn't have defined concepts that
represent those things that we just sort
of made up we've defined concepts for
things that our civilization has found
useful you know we've got a concept for
a chair or a table or something like
this and what's sort of interesting to
me and the evolution of these things you
know if you look at human language it
evolves based on the things that show up
in the world like a world a word like
podcast didn't exist before those things
kind of showed up in the world and and
now when we say podcast that comes with
a whole bundle of kind of conceptual
sort of things we we think about but the
the fact that that word was worth
inventing was a consequence of something
that existed in the world but once we've
invented that word then we can sort of
reason in terms of it and build things
on top of it and that's very much the
same process as what goes on in
designing computational language that
you know once you've invented subset map
or something then you think of lots of
kinds of I don't know functional
programming operations or whatever it is
in terms of that concept that one has
now invented so it's a it's a it's sort
of a funny loop that goes between the
what gets described in a language and
what people choose to build and then
what people choose to build being what
ends up defining what's worth defining
in a
language so an interesting example of
this computational essay to bring it
back is like your book right so your
book I feel like we I have to plug it
since your publicist set this button so
you know like I'm looking at an essay
here called the data science of Facebook
and it's sort of you know I think it's a
good example of what you're talking
about earlier like it's prose then mixed
with like calculations and graphics
right right I mean that the version of
that that there's there's this one it's
probably an online version of this that
actually has the code oh that one that
one
unfortunately the code is there the data
we cannot expose for that particular one
but I mean the the the raw data this was
a this was a thing we did back in 2012
or so Facebook used to have this very
rich API that they exposed where and we
provided something in wolf malphur where
you could go and kind of find out what
Facebook knew about you and it kind of
generated this I know it was 30 40 page
book effectively of kind of you know
where your friends live what um what the
popular words on their feeds were and
all sorts of things I don't remember all
the details but for a while we were just
like people would connect to the
WolframAlpha we could connect
WolframAlpha to their Facebook accounts
and it would generate all the stuff and
then we throw the data away in an hour
this essay was the result of doing some
analysis of things like you know what is
the distribution of Ages of people's
friends relative to their own age and
you kind of see it's very tightly peaked
but until people get to about age 35 and
then there starts to be a little a
little an earlier peak which gets bigger
which is people friending there at least
back in those days people friending
their kids and their kids friends and
things like this it's super interesting
as an example of kind of the thing
you're talking about so I I recommend
people to check out that book so this
has been great this was good I you know
we got to talk about some lots of nice
computational language stuff which I was
like talking about and hopefully your
your
we'll find of interest I mean that I
think you know one of the challenges in
what we're doing is that it's different
from what's been done you know what's
done elsewhere and so it's funny I you
know if I look at things I've done in my
life there are quite a few things where
I figured out something that I thought
was important like the use of programs
instead of equations to model natural
systems and so on a bunch of other kinds
of things and then people say oh no they
can't possibly work oh no we don't
understand it etc etcetera etcetera and
then you know a couple of decades goes
by and yep that's how people think about
things now and it's kind of interesting
to see this inexorable thing that
happens because you know I I think my
sort of self-assessment of my ability to
figure out what's going to happen is
that I'm pretty good I don't necessarily
get the time scale right but I'm pretty
good at figuring out what's going to
happen and I think with this whole
computational language thing
it's absolutely inevitable I mean that
this way of setting things up is what
people are going to become used to and
there's going to be sort of a level of
computational language literacy that
starts to develop and that's going to be
the future it may be a while but it's
kind of it's kind of amazing how much
one has to kind of sort of explain it
explain it explain it over and over
again and it's funny how the world works
cuz you know you can explain these
things a bunch of times and people don't
get it and then you know a decade goes
by and sort of it slowly seeps into kind
of general consciousness and then
eventually people think it's obvious
right and so you know this will be
obvious one day but it isn't yet I mean
it's like like notebooks for example
which I always thought were completely
obvious you know back when we invented
them and then people were saying oh no
this is a you know how can we possibly
understand this as an interface to
computer system and then you know in
that case nearly three decades went by
and it's like oh yeah of course this is
the obvious way to do it well thank you
so much for your time
Stephen this is Adam Lorne Balfe from
software engineering radio thank you
everyone for listening thanks for
listening the SC radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website @ SC - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website that will reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio.com you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of SU radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]